OZ PRODUCTION
DARK WATER
HITOMI KUROKI
RIO KANNO MIREI OGUCHI
ASAMI MIZUKAWA
PRODUCER TAKASHIGE ICHISE
ORIGINAL STORY BY KOJI SUZUKI
SCREENPLAY YOSHIHIRO NAKAMURA KENICHI SUZUKI
DIRECTED BY HIDEO NAKATA
And tomorrow , we can practice singing , okay ?
Okay , see you tomorrow ! Okay !
Okay , see you tomorrow !
Yoshimi , who 's coming to get you ?
Miss Yoshimi Matsubara .
Well , your husband has no objections on the division of property .
So it is our daughter ?
Yes .
He 's absolutely insistent that he won 't give up custody .
I wonder why he 's saying this now ?
Up to this point , he 's never taken care of her , not even once .
Perhaps it 's just that you 've never noticed .
He may have , in his own way ...
No , that 's not it at all !
Every year , he forgets her birthday !
Where are you living ?
I 'm looking for a place for my daughter and myself right now .
But I 'll be deciding this week .
Just a small question .
Certainly .
Is it true that you once received psychiatric treatment ?
Did he tell you that ?
Yes .
That was before we were married .
Over ten years ago , now .
I was working proofreading novels at the time , and ...
You mean correcting spelling mistakes , that sort of thing ?
Yes .
And some of the novels I was working on then
were extremely graphic and sadistic .
So it was a distraction to your work ?
No , you see , the content was just so horrible !
And I had to read them over and over again .
So that 's when you started going for treatment ?
Yes .
I see .
Is that going to ...
Oh , no , that shouldn 't present a problem .
You know , I ...
I haven 't had any problems at all since then .
It 's all right .
And unless something major occurs ,
the mother usually has the advantage
when the child is six years old or younger .
Right .
My being treated before ,
that doesn 't matter anymore .
Hey , a fact is a fact .
What 's wrong with telling the truth ?
I don 't think it will get you very far now .
Go straight along the river .
- Right here ? - Yes .
Thank you very much .
Are you tired ?
This next one is going to be the last , okay ?
All right , I 'm going on ahead .
Iku-chan !
What do you think this room is for ?
Is that where you eat ?
How about this one ?
Where you sleep ?
How about this little one over here ?
That 's my room !
Okay , I 'm off to go see Iku-chan 's room ! Bye !
Hey !
How many floors are there ?
Gee , I don 't know ...
Can you count them ?
One , two , three , four , five ...
So , what do you think ?
A real bargain , I 'd say .
We 'll think about it .
Please do !
Ms. Matsubara ?
Yes .
I 've been waiting for you .
Please , come in .
The apartment manager lives here too .
So you can feel safe , even coming home at night .
Disappointed ?
It IS a bit old .
But it 's solidly built , you know .
Please .
Mr. Kamiya !
I told you to wipe this up .
I 'm sorry , it looks like a bucket of water spilled earlier .
After you .
Which way ?
Here we are .
After you .
How old is your daughter ?
Iku-chan , how old are you ?
Almost six !
Oh , then you 're going to be a kindergartener .
Yup !
Mama , where 's my room ?
How about this one over here ?
All right !
From here , you can walk to kindergarten .
Next week , interior decorators are going to come in ,
and replace all of the wallpaper .
It will look so new you won 't recognize it .
The humidity in here is unreal .
Well , with the rain that we 've been having ...
Most people use this room as a bedroom .
Oh , that 's right ,
I haven 't shown you the kitchen yet , have I ?
Please .
The kitchen will be made up nice soon too .
You 'll find it easy to use .
It looked like that last family liked this place too .
" The early bird catches the worm . "
Oh , really ?
It 's just the two of you , right ?
Yes .
Oh , then there 's plenty of room !
A real steal .
Iku-chan ?
Maybe she went outside ?
I 'm going to go check .
Iku-chan ?
Excuse me , has my little girl been here ?
We haven 't seen her .
I see ...
Baron , have you seen a girl ?
He says he hasn 't either .
Iku-chan !
That 's my daughter !
Which floor was that ?
Can 't tell . They all look the same .
Iku-chan !
Mama !
What were you doing ?
I was looking all over for you .
Where did you get this ?
It was lying on the ground .
Where ?
Over there .
There aren 't any children living here now .
Well , maybe some children came over to play .
It 's your lucky day .
No !
It 's not right .
We don 't know who these belong to .
You don 't have to work so hard .
No problem !
LOST AND FOUND
Mine !
Hey !
Come back here !
You silly !
The sound really echoes , huh ?
Gotta be careful , right ?
What the ...
Count to ten on each tooth !
I am counting !
- Cheese ! - Cheese !
Everyone , I 'd like to introduce our new friend , Ikuko Matsubara .
Nice to meet you , I 'm Ikuko Matsubara .
You don 't seem very excited .
I 'm Ikuko Matsubara !
All right ! Pleased to meet you !
Welcome ! Which floor , Ma 'am ?
The first floor , please .
Certainly .
Huh ?
Excuse me .
There 's water leaking from our ceiling .
I 'm Yoshimi Matsubara , we just moved into apartment 305 .
There 's a wet spot on my ceiling , and water is dripping down from it .
Well , the building is very old , you see .
So it gets a little rickety .
Okay ...
And so ...
I 'll make a note of it in the log .
All right , everyone !
Quiet down and listen up .
I want to introduce our newest friend on her first day !
Now , can you be energetic as you tell us your name ?
Nice to meet you , I 'm Ikuko Matsubara !
Now let 's all be friendly to her , okay ?
Okay !
Please .
Thank you . Please .
We believe in giving children the freedom to do what they desire .
This is our basic educational philosophy .
All of our children are really outgoing .
Ikuko will make friends in no time .
- Please take care of her . - Not a problem .
Here you are .
Oh , thank you .
- Please , go ahead . - Thank you for the drink .
Principal , Kobayashi is here .
I hear that you called Ms. Tsushima stupid .
That 's no good ,
you 're going to be an elementary school student soon .
You said it to Kusano and Uesugi , right ?
That I 'm stupid .
Why is Ms. Tsushima stupid ?
What was it that you said ?
" Ms. Tsushima is stupid because she 's fat . "
That 's what you said , right ?
What 's that all about ?
Is everyone who is overweight stupid ?
Well ?
What are you crying for ?
Hey , Kobayashi !
Yes , why are you crying ?
Is it our fault ?
Well , that 's not it , it 's nobody 's fault but your own .
Hello ?
The place might be old , but I really doubt that that 's the cause .
I think that it might be a plumbing leak or something
from somewhere above us .
Maybe from the room right above you .
That 's what I thought , so I went up and checked ,
but no one answered .
Thank you for the food .
I understand , I 'll tell the apartment manager myself tomorrow .
No , you see , he won 't lift a finger , that 's why I called you .
But I 'm not involved with management , you see .
But water is dripping from my ceiling .
Okay , see you tomorrow !
Sorry to keep you waiting , I was a little tied up .
Where were we ?
Oh , yes , Ms. Yoshimi Matsubara .
You have previous experience , correct ?
I worked up until six years ago .
I see , I see ...
At Sanyu Publishing , quite a large company .
As you can see , we 're a small publisher .
Why did you leave Sanyu ?
I got married and had a child .
Oh , I see , I see .
Are you sure you 'd be okay with a little place like this ?
The pay wouldn 't be like what you got before , you know .
Well , I 'm in a situation right now
where I really want to start working soon .
Of course , I don 't mean taking a job just anywhere ...
That 's all right , I understand .
I 'm sorry .
Mr. Kono !
Yes ?
Excuse me again , please .
I 'm sorry for having to leave so many times .
Yes ?
Okay , goodbye !
Hello ?
What 's going on ?
Yoshimi 's been waiting here by herself all this ...
What ? You can 't just ...
So who 's coming to pick her up today ?
I see .
Yoshimi-chan !
Today , they said that your father 's coming to get you .
So just wait a little longer , okay ?
What about my mama ?
Your mama ? Well , your mama ...
Sir , even if you say that ,
there is just no way for us to deal with it ...
Ms. Matsubara ?
Oh , yes , I worked at Sanyu until six years ago , when I had my child .
My job was proofreading and revisions , and ...
I look forward to working with you .
Right .
Hey , wait a second , Ms. Matsubara ?
Iku-chan !
Iku-chan ...
CHILD MISSING
MITSUKO KAWAI
BORN NOVEMBER 3 , 1993 ( 5 YEARS OLD ) HEIGHT 116 CM , WEIGHT 20 KG LONG , BLACK HAIR , WEARING A YELLOW RAINCOAT ( WITH HOOD ) LAST SEEN ON JULY 14 , 1999 ...
Iku-chan !
Mama !
Don 't just do whatever you want !
What do you mean , " whatever I want ? "
What are you doing ? You didn 't even go to pick her up !
This has nothing to do with you !
Waiting there all alone ...
Do you know how that feels ? !
We 're going home .
Let 's go .
This is pretty .
Yes , it 's pretty , it 's pretty .
What does it look like to you ?
A flower ?
Do you want to try that ?
Let 's get some on the way home .
Where should we set the fireworks off ?
We 'd get in trouble on the balcony , right ?
Mama ?
I 'm okay with being with just you , Mama .
Did Papa say something to you ?
I 'm sorry .
As long as you 're with me , Iku-chan ,
I 'll be okay , no matter what happens .
You have one new message .
This is Kono , head of personnel at Mitsuba Publishing .
I 'm really sorry for all of the commotion at your interview today .
In any case , I was thinking , that if you would like ,
we would like for you to take over the proofreading and revisions ...
No way !
What ?
I got the job !
You got the job ? You did it !
All right ! I did it !
You did it !
Would you like to go to the top floor , Ma 'am ?
Yes , please .
Fourth floor , toys .
Going up !
Okay !
Let 's go !
Okay .
No !
No , don 't !
Ow ! That hurts , ow !
There , I win !
But that 's not yours , Mit-chan .
That 's no fair .
What ?
I like this one , so I 'll give you this one , Mit-chan .
That 's okay , right ?
Iku-chan , turn off the water and come on out .
But she loves the bath . She 's going to stay in it forever .
Come on now , time to come out .
Okay , let 's play hide and seek !
Yay !
First you start with rock ,
rock , paper , scissors !
Okay , Mao-chan 's it !
One ... two ... three ... four ...
Hey , can I hide here too ?
This is our spot . Hide over there .
I 'm ready !
What happened ?
Well ...
She suddenly threw up and collapsed ?
That 's never happened before .
You probably forced her to do something , didn 't you ?
No , not at all ...
You two ...
Just what have you done to my child ?
We haven 't done anything at all .
But ...
Ma 'am , please try and calm down .
Please , please .
Lately , I 've heard that Ikuko has been behaving strangely .
Apparently , she talks to herself a lot .
I also hear that you 're divorced .
That must be affecting her .
We see this often with children of divorced parents .
MITSUKO , COME HOME SOON
As a matter of fact , she used to behave oddly too .
Although in Mitsuko 's case ,
her mother suddenly just left their house , and left her behind .
You 've never heard of her ?
About the girl who disappeared two years ago ?
Mitsuko Kawai ?
She was one of our children here .
Is she still missing ?
Yes .
I still think that she was kidnapped by some perverted individual .
Excuse me ?
Apparently , you 're late picking Ikuko up from kindergarten every day ?
That can 't be ... " Every day " ?
Is that incorrect ?
Well , sometimes I get there late , because of work , but really ...
" Every day " ?
Who told you that ?
And is it true you yanked on your daughter 's arm
and dislocated her shoulder ?
Dislocated it ?
Why no , of course not !
What about your experiences in wandering about at night ,
like you were sleepwalking ?
Do you deny that ?
It happened when I was a child .
My parents had divorced .
Apparently , I did such things without realizing it .
But it was only for a short period of time .
Well , I assure you that it would not happen now .
If the mother cannot show that she is capable of raising the child ...
Don 't just talk about anything you want to !
Why are you shouting about " talk about anything I want to ? "
- But you did , didn 't you ? - Please , let 's remain calm .
Who is this ?
I 'm Mr. Hamada 's lawyer , Masato Nishioka .
Using a guy like this ... Doing things like spying on us !
Hey , I 'm just worried about Ikuko .
What are you saying , now of all times ?
I don 't care how you rationalize it , stop playing dirty !
Please , both of you .
We need to set the next date .
Right , sorry .
So it was you ...
And the bag , you put it there .
What ?
The red bag on the roof !
Why did you do that ? !
What are you talking about ?
Why ? !
Ms. Matsubara !
Please cut it out !
Let 's go inside , Mr. Hamada .
Are you all right ?
I take it you 're still in the middle of mediations .
If you let them see you like this ,
they 'll think you 're unstable
which can only hurt you .
My secretary is off today , so this may be a little strong .
Whoops , I forgot the milk and sugar .
If they take my daughter away from me , I ...
Your husband seems pretty serious .
We don 't know where he 'll move against you .
They say in cases with children under the age of six ,
the mother has the advantage .
But if you continue along this path ,
and your body and mind continue to weaken ,
it will be nearly impossible for you to retain custody .
In any case , now is the most critical time .
If you wish to continue living with your daughter ,
the first thing you need to do is pull yourself together .
Right ...
Come now .
We can 't get very far with you being down like that .
It 'll be all right .
Let 's do our best together .
Thank you very much .
Did she eat her lunch ?
Sure did .
Girls are just the cutest things .
Auntie , leaving already ?
Yeah , I have to buy something on the way home .
You know how he leaves it all to me .
Sorry , I know it 's a long way .
You 're the only one I can ask , Auntie .
It 's all right .
You 've done well with Ikuko .
A far cry from the mother you had .
My sister just couldn 't think of anyone but herself .
Okay , see you later .
Thank you .
See you later .
Iku-chan ?
Iku-chan !
Iku-chan ...
Mama !
Iku-chan ?
Are you there ?
It 's me .
Is Ikuko with you ?
No .
Don 't lie .
I wouldn 't lie about that !
Why ? What happened ?
Yoshimi ! What 's going on ?
Iku-chan !
Iku ... Iku-chan !
Hello ? Please open up !
Hello ? !
Iku-chan , are you in there ?
Iku-chan ?
Iku-chan ...
Iku-chan , are you in here ?
Iku-chan ?
Iku-chan !
Iku-chan ! Iku-chan ! Iku-chan !
SHOJI AND MITSUKO KAWAI
Mitsuko Kawai ...
CHILD MISSING
MITSUKO KAWAI
May I come in ?
Certainly .
Pardon me .
What are you doing ?
We 're moving out .
If you do that ,
then Ikuko will have to change kindergartens again .
That 's right .
Why not wait a while , until the deliberation is over ?
That 's impossible .
Ms. Matsubara ...
You know that , as it stands , we 're at a disadvantage , right ?
On top of that , if you change the situation ,
then the impression that the committee will get ...
This is no time to be saying that !
Mitsuko has returned to the apartment upstairs ,
and she 's trying to take Ikuko away !
So the door to the apartment upstairs is unlocked , correct ?
I 'm sorry to bother you at such a busy time ,
but I 'd like for you to see this .
What the ? How ?
Mr. Kamiya !
But it should be locked .
Wow , you were right .
What is this ?
The family of the girl that disappeared ,
how long ago did they leave ?
When was that ?
It was the end of last year , wasn 't it ?
The father lived here for a while by himself .
He said that his daughter would have no place to come home to .
Which means , the water in here may have been running for over half a year .
Mr. Kamiya ,
Ms. Matsubara complained to you about this once , didn 't she ?
Did you properly look into it then ?
Mr. Kamiya ,
there are a lot of people in line for your job , you know that .
There are a lot of people who can replace you .
Mr. Ohta ,
I believe she also called you .
Well , I 'm ...
Well , what about the footsteps I heard ?
Well , we know that Ikuko was in here .
So someone else could have gotten in too .
The bag was lying right here .
Did you throw the red bag away again ?
Well , I threw it away once .
But I don 't know anything about it being here again .
Maybe it 's part of some superstition .
Either way , it 's probably the work of some local kids .
But , man , look at how dirty this thing is .
Are you cleaning it properly ?
That 's the cleaning company 's job .
I can go now , right ?
Whoops .
I wonder if he 's upset ?
And then , right over there , there was someone over there .
Did you get a clear look ?
It was just for an instant , but I saw something .
But I 'll bet there was no one there when you checked .
Well , yes ...
There 's a highway over there , right ?
And there 's a neon sign on that building .
This water tank is exposed to light from all around .
So ...
If something passed in front of the light ,
it would cast a shadow on the tank .
So it wouldn 't be strange if you saw something .
Although ,
coming up here , all alone at night ,
and seeing what you saw ,
that would scare anyone .
Your husband 's lawyer has looked this over ,
and agreed to the terms .
I don 't think that this will compromise your position at all .
Thank you very much .
Just remember , this is simply a set of legal points worked out by lawyers .
So just continue with your daily routine , and try and remain focused .
I will .
Well , I think that you 'll be fine .
Ikuko .
Do you think that you 're ready to go back to kindergarten ?
I can !
Well , you seem better !
I would really like to thank you for all that you 've done .
On my own , I was so confused .
Not at all .
I believe that Ikuko needs you .
And that you need her . That 's all .
I 'm so hopeless .
I can see now that I need to be stronger .
But it 's not over yet .
The final decision will probably be made at the next session .
All right ?
In any case , if anything does happen before then ,
you must not act on your own .
Contact me immediately .
I will .
One , two , three !
All Auntie Kayo made was gruel .
That couldn 't be helped , Iku-chan , because you were sick .
But the gruel was good , right ?
I like this better .
She brought her own water to make dinner .
Her own water ?
Yeah , she said the water here is no good .
That 's true ...
The water here is a little ...
Are you sure you can go to school tomorrow ?
I can !
All right ! Then we need to get your things ready .
I 'll go and get your bag .
Iku-chan , how did this get in here ?
I don 't know .
Did you go back to the roof ?
Really , I don 't know .
I won 't get mad . I won 't get mad , so just tell me the truth .
Did you go up to the roof ?
I didn 't !
Okay .
I 'm sorry .
Connecting to personal voice mail ...
Hello , this is Kishida .
Hello , Kishida Law Offices .
Hello , my name is Yoshimi Matsubara .
Is Mr. Kishida there ?
He 's out at the moment , and we don 't expect him back today .
I see ...
Well , thank you very much . Excuse me ...
No !
Listen , don 't move .
Mama ...
Don 't follow me !
WATER TANK CLEANING LOG
JULY 14 , 1999
LAST SEEN JULY 14 , 1999
Iku-chan ...
Iku-chan !
What happened ? !
What is this ?
There we are .
I 'll never leave you alone again .
I 'll always be with you .
It 's going to be all right .
Iku-chan ?
Mama ...
Mama ?
Mama !
No !
You mustn 't come any closer !
Please stop ...
I 'm not your mama !
Mama !
Iku-chan , no !
Stop !
Ikuko !
I 'm
your mama .
Mama !
Mama , Mama !
TEN YEARS LATER
Should we call her ?
Sure .
Hello ? We 're here .
Okay , we 'll be waiting here . Bye .
Is she coming ?
Yeah , said she 'd ride her bike and be right down .
Want to buy some ice cream ?
Yeah , let 's buy some !
Let 's go ! Yeah , let 's buy some !
Ikuko , what about you ? Don 't you want any ?
What ? No , I 'm all set .
I don 't remember much from when I was in kindergarten .
Just that for a very brief period ,
I remember that I was living together with my mother .
- I 'm sorry , Ai-chan ! - Mama !
Thank goodness , right , Ai-chan ?
I 'm so sorry .
Oh , not at all .
See you tomorrow , Ai-chan .
Bye !
Bye-bye !
YOSHIMI IKUKO MATSUBARA
Mama ...
Welcome home .
You 've gotten so big .
Why ?
Nobody told me .
Have you been living here all this time ?
My friend 's house is right near here .
Everyone 's going there to hang out today .
It 's next to my old kindergarten .
The Shimizus , do you know them ?
That 's the kindergarten I went to , isn 't it ?
The one next to the bus stop .
This used to be mine .
So you 're already in high school , are you , Iku-chan ?
How time flies .
If only I had known ,
I would have come to see you long before this .
It 's all right .
Because you came to see me today .
Say , Mama ?
Do you remember when you said that as long as I was with you ,
you 'd be okay , no matter what happened ?
Of course .
Do you , well , still feel that way ?
Yes , I do .
Thank goodness .
Hey , Mama ,
could I live here , together with you ?
I 'll tell Papa myself , all right ?
I 'm sure that he 'd say okay .
He has a new wife now , and my younger sisters .
I ...
Iku-chan ...
I 'm sorry .
We can 't be together .
Mama ?
Hey , Mama ?
My mother was here all that time , protecting me .
♪ Since then , I haven 't been able to
♪ That 's right , remember you for quite some time
♪ It was because of those busy days
♪ The cluster of pains
♪ Was always deep in my heart
♪ But recently , it looks like I 've gotten better
♪ Today the sky looks like it might
♪ Reach all the way to the stars
♪ There 's no way that I could ever wipe away
♪ All of the tears in the world
♪ I 'm planning on always treasuring
♪ The small things that you taught me
♪ Hey , no matter how well
♪ I held you
♪ We 'd get interrupted all of the sudden
♪ Could it possibly be that
♪ You knew that
♪ Which is why you smiled at me then ?
♪ Hey , I wonder what kind of day
♪ Tomorrow is going to be ?
♪ There 's no way that I could ever wipe away
♪ All of the tears in the world
♪ I 'm planning on always treasuring
♪ The small things that you taught me
♪ My memories are so much , so much more distinct
♪ Than sadness or recollections
♪ The very definite words you left in my heart